<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title type="text">@mr-c snippets Blog - Posted in 2015</title>
  <id>True/blog/2015/atom.xml</id>
  <updated>2015-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <link href="True" />
  <link href="True/blog/2015/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <generator uri="http://ablog.readthedocs.org" version="0.7.12">ABlog</generator>
  <entry xml:base="True/blog/2015/atom.xml">
    <title type="text">Hoopla!</title>
    <id>True/introduction/</id>
    <updated>2015-10-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2015-10-15T00:00:00Z</published>
    <link href="True/introduction/" />
    <author>
      <name>Michael R. Crusoe</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;hoopla&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello, world! My name is &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://impactstory.org/MichaelRCrusoe&quot;&gt;Michael R. Crusoe&lt;/a&gt;;
I’m a Research Software Engineer in &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://ivory.idyll.org/lab/&quot;&gt;C. Titus Brown’s laboratory for Data
Intensive Biology&lt;/a&gt; at the University of
California, Davis in the department of Population Health and Reproduction. This
blog will be my primary communication outlet for my work with the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://common-workflow-language.github.io/&quot;&gt;Common
Workflow Language project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CWL began in July 2014 in Boston, MA, USA at the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.open-bio.org/wiki/Codefest_2014&quot;&gt;codefest preceding
the Bioinformatics Open Source Conference&lt;/a&gt;. John Chilton, from the Galaxy Team,
approached Nebojša Tijanić of Seven Bridges Genomics, about workflow
interoperability. They were quickly joined by Peter Amstutz from Curoverse,
Hervé Ménager from the Pasteur Institute and by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a bioinformatics tool developer I knew the burden that is attempting to keep
up deep integration for all the various bioinformatics processing platforms out
there. I had complained to John Chilton several times before about how
unrealistic it was to expect scientific tool authors to describe their tools to
each system separately. When I saw the group forming I jumped at the chance to
promote a portable way to describe how to run command line tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I take no credit for it, I am very proud the the working group that grew
around the CWL released their second draft at this year’s BOSC and it was my
pleasure to &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sF4DJVUcjnU&quot;&gt;present the work of the team at the conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;funding&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Funding&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the group has established itself and we are attracting even more
projectis who want to work with us, it is time for the group to mature and grow.
At BOSC this year I was vocal and open about the fact that there was no
specific funding for the CWL as a project. To my delight leadership from both
Curoverse and Seven Bridges Genomics reached out to see what could be done. I
am happy to announce that Curoverse has written myself, John Chilton, and
Carrie Ganote (Indiana University, Bloomington) into their recently submitted
Phase II SBIR proposal. &lt;strong&gt;On a more immediate basis SBG has given UC Davis an
unrestricted gift to support me working full time on the project for the next
six months&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working with Brandi Davis-Dusenbery, Scientific Program Manager at SBG, I
developed both a set of six month goals for the project and a longer term
vision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;six-month-plan&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Six Month Plan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuation of the working group meetings held online every 2-3 weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CWL workshop at the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;www.festivalofgenomicscalifornia.com/hackathon-describing-bioinformatics-tools-and-workflows-using-common-workflow-language/&quot;&gt;Festival of Genomics, California&lt;/a&gt;
on November 3rd.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/d/msg/common-workflow-language/oNzbSj7hz7E/ymU4fz2CBgAJ&quot;&gt;CWL codefest in Santa Clara&lt;/a&gt;
on November 4th.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be meeting with the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://agaveapi.co/&quot;&gt;Agave Platform&lt;/a&gt; team in
November to see about harmonizing our efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One to three additional meetups, workshops, or hackathons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A baseline sustainability report on the project will be written and used to
further prioritize plans. This report will follow in spirit the
&lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://figshare.com/articles/Criteria_based_assessment_of_the_khmer_suite/1558321&quot;&gt;Criteria-based assessment of the khmer suite&lt;/a&gt;.
In addition, specific community engagement metrics will be reported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Group goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. A system of project governance is agreed upon and set up through a
community-centered process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A US charitable foundation is set up and it owns assets on behalf of the
community as directed by the new shared governance structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This foundation is able to provide direct support to contributors from
donated funds and/or funds raised through competitive grant applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot; start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Version 1 of the specification is released.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A process for defining extensions is agreed upon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot; start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At least 3 implementations of CWL are available and input from groups
implementing the spec is incorporated to the specification as extensions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A manuscript or whitepaper describing CWL is formalized and ready for
submission to a peer-reviewed journal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A robust validator is available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User-facing guides on tool and workflow description are grown via several
collaborative tech events (codefests, hackathons, site visits, workshops)
where community members teach/work with newcomers on some aspect of the CWL.
These events include dedicated time and space to execute on lessons learned
by updating documentation, issue tracker management, specification &amp;amp;
implementation work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A simple dashboard is built that lists the number of tools (workflows)
described in using the CWL on the main page of the CWL. Other dashboards
show how these tool descriptions’ tests (in the form of workflows) are
passing on the various implementations. The implementations themselves are
also regularly tested using a conformance suite.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;section&quot; id=&quot;long-term-goals&quot;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Long Term Goals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;arabic simple&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CWL Workflows are the preferred way to fulfill the now-ubiquitous journal and
funder requirements for computational reproducibility and reusability in the
life sciences and beyond. (supplying a CWL compliant workflow version fulfills
journal requirements for reproducibility and fast-tracks publications)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scientific tool authors ship CWL tool definitions as a matter of course. Most
of them are made automatically when the authors use standard libraries. For
some tools the community provides the definitions. Regardless of the source,
the CWL tool definitions are shipped alongside each tool when installed using
the major end-user package managers (Debian, RedHat, Conda, LinuxBrew).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workflow authors/users have a variety of tools to create, edit, and visualize
workflows; both standalone as part of complete workflow systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What constitutes a valid workflow/tool description is non-controversial.
Automated checkers and community support are widely available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Certifications of compliance are issued to conformant platforms in an automated
fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The CWL Project has a perfect score using the &lt;a class=&quot;reference external&quot; href=&quot;http://www.software.ac.uk/software-evaluation-guide&quot;&gt;Software Sustainability
Institute’s criteria-based software evaluation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The regular participants in the CWL project and leadership are diverse both by
demographics (with global demographics as the target) and by skillset / field /
role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
